{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Born Odo of Châtillon, this pope studied at Reims under Bruno of Segni. This pope condemned King Philip the First of France for an adulterous union, and the tenure of this pope included an influential council at Piacenza which addressed political crises in the Byzantine Empire. At another council, this pope announced \"Deus Vult!\" or \"God Wills It!\" in a call to Catholic to assist eastern Christians. For ten points, name this pope who, at the Council of Claremont called the First Crusade.",
      "answer": [
        "Pope Urban the Second",
        "Urbanus the Second",
        "Otho de Lagery"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization inspired the name of an American group that used the slogan \"Don't vote, revolt!\" Martyrs and soldiers were among the Five Categories for members of this group, who aimed to combat a series of outdated beliefs known as the Four Olds. \"Capitalist roaders\" were targeted by this group, whose earliest members came from a school linked with Tsinghua University. For ten points, name this organization of students that supported Chairman Mao.",
      "answer": [
        "Red Guards",
        "Hóng Wèibīng"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "\"Training the young\" and \"Engaging in community activities\" were among the six categories that all activities in this municipality were thought to have attempted to achieve. A work about this place In Transition examined \"Cultural Conflicts,\" and this place was described as \"a community as small as 30-odd thousand.\" This location was the subject of fieldwork by Robert and Helen Lynd which utilized an \"approach of [a] cultural anthropologist.\" For ten points, identify this American town that was the subject of a set of sociological studies in Indiana.",
      "answer": [
        "Middletown",
        "Muncie",
        "Middletown in Transition: A Study in Cultural Conflicts"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These Olympic games hosted equestrian events in Stockholm due to the strict quarantine rules of its host country. These Olympics became infamous for a water polo match called the “Blood in the Water,\" and these Olympics games, the southernmost ever, were also the first held outside of Europe or North America. Eight countries boycotted these games due to the Suez Crisis and the Soviet invasion of Hungary. For ten points, name these Olympic games which were held in Australia.",
      "answer": [
        "1956 Summer Olympics",
        "Melbourne Olympics"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this region, Manuel Fernández Silvestre was killed during a military action that ended in retreat. In July of 1909, forces from this region attacked workers building a rail-bridge aiming to provide access to iron mines at Melilla. A confederate republic that existed in this region from 1921 to 1926 was led by Abd el- Krim, and this region named a war that resisted colonialism and the Treaty of Fez. For ten points, identify this mountainous region where a joint French and Spanish force fought Berber tribes in northern Morocco.",
      "answer": [
        "Rif or Rif Mountains",
        "Arrif",
        "Rif War 1 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer outlined a devout adherence to Catholicism in the historical opera Saint François d'Assise. This composer included a part for a type of early electronic instrument called an ondes Martenot for the Turangalîla Symphony, and parts for clarinet, violin, and cello were played by captives at Stalag Seven-A in a World War Two-inspired quartet. For ten points, name this French composer who drew on experiences as a prisoner for war for his Quartet for the End of Time.",
      "answer": "Olivier Messiaen or Olivier Eugène Prosper Charles Messiaen"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician gained fame for leading an investment banking firm that lost the most employees in the September Eleventh attacks. This politician is known for his advocacy of cryptocurrencies such as Tether, and, with Linda McMahon, this politician served as co-chair of Donald Trump's 2024 transition team. This politician initially jockeyed against Scott Bessent for the role of secretary of the treasury. For ten points, name this chair and CEO of Cantor Fitzgerald who serves as Donald Trump's secretary of commerce.",
      "answer": "Howard Lutnick or Howard William Lutnick"
    },
    {
      "question": "Implemented in 1921, this policy eliminated the practice of grain requisition and created a group of namesake \"men,\" a class of private merchants who prospered briefly. This policy replaced War Communism and allowed small-scale private enterprises while maintaining state control of major industries. This policy was ended by Josef Stalin's rise to power and the First Five-Year Plan in 1928. For ten points, name this Vladimir Lenin-initiated Soviet policy to create free markets and capitalistic elements under control of the state.",
      "answer": [
        "New Economic Plan or NEP",
        "NEPmen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "World Trade Center hero Rick Rescorla appeared on the cover of a book about this battle, in which the Boeing B-52 Stratofortress was first used for tactical support. Morley Safer reported on this battle, in which Hal Moore's men were involved at landing zone X-Ray. This battle was the subject of a book by Joseph Galloway titled We Were Soldiers Once... and Young, and this battle occurred during the 1965 Pleiku Campaign. For ten points, identify this first major battle fought between the U.S. Army and the People's Army of Vietnam.",
      "answer": "Battle of Ia Drang ] Valley"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country was first encountered by Europeans when Commodore John Byron discovered its northern islands in 1765. The HMS Dolphin and HMS Tamar visited this modern country during a circumnavigation voyage under Captain Samuel Wallis in 1767. After becoming a British protectorate in 1892, this country was the site of nuclear tests on Christmas Island during the 1950s. For ten points, identify this Pacific island nation that was known as the Gilbert Islands before gaining independence in 1979.",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Kiribati ]",
        "phonetic pronunciations"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Laurent-Désiré Kabila overthrew this dictator, and also participated in the earlier, Cuban-supported Simba rebellion against him. This leader promoted a policy of Authenticité, which included removing Western names from places such as Stanleyville, which was renamed to Kisangani. Patrice Lumumba was a political opponent of this leader, who was known for wearing leopard-skin hats. For ten points, name this leader who served as the dictator of Zaire, or the Democratic Republic of the Congo, from 1965 to 1997.",
      "answer": "Mobutu Sese Seko"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 589, the third church council held in this city officially codified the filioque clause. In 1226, construction began on the Primatial Cathedral of Saint Mary in this city, which, for nearly 200 years, was the capital of the Visigothic Kingdom. The siege of the Alcázar occurred in this city during its country's civil war, and this city was home to a specific alloy used by Hannibal's forces during the Punic War. For ten points, name this city in central Spain known for making swords with its namesake steel.",
      "answer": [
        "Toledo",
        "Toledo steel"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This treaty followed a civil war in which two brothers, Charles and Louis, allied against a third, who lost but was able to retain control of a \"Middle\" Kingdom covering Burgundy. Lothair, a signatory to this treaty, later concluded the similar Treaty of Prüm, creating the Kingdom of Italy for his son Louis the Younger. Two kingdoms created by this treaty, which was written following the death of Louis the Pious, developed into France and Germany. For ten points, name this 843 treaty which divided Charlemagne's empire.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Verdun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the Treaty of Verdun, Lothair the First received this imperial city in North Rhine-Westphalia, the site of Charlemagne's primary residence. The remaining portion of that residence in this city is known as the Palatine Chapel.",
        "answer": "Aachen"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Prior to this battle, one commander established Fort Recovery at the spot of Arthur St. Clair's defeat, and William Campbell closed a British fort to the losing side following this battle. Due to heavy rains, many fighters on one side of this battle were away breaking their fast, leading to a disorganized ambush along the Maumee River. For ten points, identify this battle in which Northwestern Confederacy warriors led by Blue Jacket and Little Turtle were defeated by \"Mad\" Anthony Wayne.",
        "answer": "Battle of Fallen Timbers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Ohio campaign, Anthony Wayne was consistently undermined by this subordinate, who was posthumously revealed to be an agent for the Spanish Crown. As Governor of Louisiana, this officer participated in Burr's Conspiracy.",
        "answer": "James Wilkinson 3 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This speech was republished by Frances Dana Barker Gage during the Civil War in a version which changed the speaker's Jersey Dutch verbiage. Marius Robinson published a more accurate version of this speech in the Anti-Slavery Bugle. This speech was delivered at a suffragette conference in Akron, Ohio, and this speech involves the repetition of a question based on the Wedgwood anti-slavery medallion. For ten points, name this speech given by Sojourner Truth in 1851 that decried racism and sexism against Black women.",
        "answer": "\"Ain't I a Woman?\""
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Dutch was also spoken in this town in Upstate New York, which was the birthplace of U.S. president Martin Van Buren, providing one of his nicknames.",
        "answer": [
          "Kinderhook",
          "Old Kinderhook"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Nubian expedition of this king failed for lack of supplies, but produced a Nile trading post and tribute of ivory and an okapi. The Phoenician sailors of this king refused to attack Carthage, and this king lost a whole army sent against Siwa due to a sandstorm. After killing the Apis bull and violating Zoroastrianism by burning the mummy of Pharaoh Amasis, this king was killed in a revolt by a Magian [[MAY-jee-uhn]] pretending to be his brother. For ten points, name this son of Cyrus, the second Achaemenid king who conquered Egypt.",
        "answer": "Cambyses the Second or Kanbuziya the Second"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the noted accomplishments of Cambyses the Second was the conquest of this eastern region of Libya, which later became a Roman province with Crete and was declared an autonomous region of Libya in 2012 by its own \"Transitional Council.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Cyrenaica",
          "Crete and Cyrenaica",
          "Cyrenaica Transitional Council"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Supreme Court’s ruling in Cooper v. Anderson ruled this concept ineffective. The editor of the Richmond News-Leader, James J. Kilpatrick, resuscitated this concept in response to the Supreme Court’s ruling in Brown v. Board of Education. James Madison first proposed this concept in his Virginia Resolution, which opposed the Alien and Sedition Acts. For ten points, identify this Constitutional precept in which a state government places itself between a federal mandate and the citizens of that state.",
        "answer": "interposition"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Supreme Court case Cooper v. Aaron rejected efforts in this U.S. state, which was governed by Orval Faubus, to bypass court-mandated school integration using interposition.",
        "answer": "Arkansas 4 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Khamsa, or “Five Treasures,” is a book of poems by Nizami, an author from Ganja in this modern- day country. Shah Ismail the First wrote over 1,400 verses in this country’s local language, which coincided with the blossoming of the ashik traveling bard culture. A national novel from this country features an antagonist named Nacharyan and describes an interreligious relationship which begins in the 1910s Caucasus, with a major development in the plot involving the Bolshevik Revolution in Russia. The pseudonymous Kurban Said wrote Ali and Nino about, for ten points, what country’s capital of Baku?",
        "answer": "Azerbaijan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of Ali and Nino's eponymous characters, Ali Khan, is of Persian descent and Shiite faith, which was adopted by Persia during the rule of this early modern \"gunpowder\" dynasty.",
        "answer": "Safavids"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The wife of this battle's victorious leader names a trophy awarded for \"gentlemanly conduct\" in the National Hockey League. During this battle, troops used the creeping barrage tactic and advanced behind specialized formations nicknamed \"the Glide.\" Rehearsals on full-scale terrain models helped troops capture a heavily fortified position during this first battle of the Nivelle Offensive in the department of Pas-de-Calais. For ten points, identify this 1917 battle of World War One, which is credited with establishing Canada's reputation as an elite fighting force.",
        "answer": "Battle of Vimy Ridge"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This general, who was made Viscount of Vimy after the battle, was later involved in a namesake 1926 constitutional crisis when he refused William Lyon Mackenzie King's request to dissolve parliament, prompting reforms to the Crown's role in Dominion affairs.",
        "answer": "Julian Byng"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The leader of this event was brought to one empire's capital in an iron cage after defeats at Tatishcheva Fortress and Tsaritsyn. That leader of this event gained support by promising to restore the Old Believer faith and abolish the poll tax. Fellow rebels betrayed the leader of this event, who claimed to have been a royal who escaped assassination. For ten points, identify this 1773 to 1775 event in which a Cossack pretender claiming to be Peter the Third rebelled against Catherine the Great.",
        "answer": [
          "Pugachev's Rebellion",
          "Cossack Rebellion before \"Cossack\" is mentioned",
          "Peasants' War 1773 to 1775 before date range is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Russian author interviewed Pugachev's survivors while researching his historical novel The Captain's Daughter, which depicts the rebellion through the eyes of a young officer.",
        "answer": "Alexander Pushkin 5 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This person wrote a text called On Sizes and Distances, which estimated the radii of the Sun and Moon and their distances from Earth. This person was cited in chapter three of the Almagest due to work with epicycles, and he compared the longitudes of two stars to prior observations in order to discover the precession of the equinoxes. For ten points, name this Greek astronomer and mathematician who hailed from Rhodes and is considered the founder of trigonometry.",
        "answer": "Hipparchus of Rhodes or Hípparkhos"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hipparchus was known for criticizing this Greek polymath who is considered the founder of geography, calculated the Earth's circumference, and developed a conceptual \"sieve\" to find prime numbers.",
        "answer": [
          "Eratosthenes of Cyrene",
          "Sieve of Eratosthenes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle was marked by a defection of 20,000 Karluk mercenaries to the winning side, and this battle was preceded a generation earlier by the Battle of Aksu. This battle was immediately preceded by one side gaining control of the Gilgit region, after which the winning side occupied Merv. Prisoners taken at this battle may have spread papermaking technology westward, and its winning side was assisted by the Tibetan Empire. For ten points, name this frontier battle in which a small Tang army was defeated by the nascent Abbasid Caliphate.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Talas River or Dáluósī Zhànyì",
          "or Maʿrakat nahr Ṭalās"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Talas occurred during this emperor’s lengthy reign. He also established the Jiedushi system and was forced into retirement by the An Lushan Rebellion.",
        "answer": [
          "Tang Xuanzong ] or Mysterious Ancestor",
          "or Li Sanlang",
          "Brilliant Emperor before mentioned"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Civil Rights Activists",
      "prompt": "Concerning American civil rights activists, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Civil rights leader who gave the \"I Have a Dream\" speech and was assassinated in Memphis.",
          "answer": "Martin Luther King, Jr. or MLK"
        },
        {
          "question": "Alabama capital, to which activists led a march from Selma across the Edmund Pettis Bridge.",
          "answer": "Montgomery"
        },
        {
          "question": "Southern university in Oxford, where James Meredith enrolled with the help of federal marshals.",
          "answer": "University of Mississippi or Ole Miss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim minister, also known as el-Hajj Malik el-Shabazz, who was assassinated in 1965.",
          "answer": [
            "Malcolm X or Malcolm Little",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Labor unionist who organized the March on Washington with Bayard Rustin.",
          "answer": "Asa Philip Randolph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former pastor who became mayor of Atlanta and the first Black U.S. ambassador to the U.N.",
          "answer": "Andrew Young or Andrew Jackson Young Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Campaign led by SCLC president Ralph Abernathy, during which protesters constructed Resurrection City.",
          "answer": "Poor People's Campaign or Poor People's March on Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who trained Freedom Summer volunteers and said, \"I am sick and tired of being sick and tired.\"",
          "answer": "Fannie Lou Hamer or Fannie Lou Townsend 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "English Civil War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the English Civil War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Body part that was removed with an axe from Charles the First during his execution.",
          "answer": [
            "head",
            "beheaded and similar answers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislative body that defeated the monarchy, which included the Houses of Lords and Commons.",
          "answer": [
            "Parliament of England",
            "Long Parliament"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the New Model Army, who ruled as lord protector after the war.",
          "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic-majority island invaded by the New Model Army in the 1650s following the war.",
          "answer": [
            "Ireland or Éire",
            "or Airlann"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Royalist cathedral city stronghold in Northern England, besieged by the Covenanters for two months in 1644.",
          "answer": [
            "York",
            "Siege of York"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1645 Royalist defeat in West Northamptonshire, which effectively ended their hope for victory in the war.",
          "answer": "Battle of Naseby"
        },
        {
          "question": "German-English prince and calvary officer who lost at Marston Moor and names a port city near the Alaskan panhandle.",
          "answer": [
            "Prince Rupert of the Rhine or Duke of Cumberland",
            "Prince Rupert Land"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First pitched battle of the war, fought in Warwickshire in October, 1642.",
          "answer": "Battle of Edgehill 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Uruguay",
      "prompt": "Concerning the history of Uruguay, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Bovine animals, which were introduced by the Spanish and provide beef for export.",
          "answer": "cattle or cows"
        },
        {
          "question": "Right given to same-sex couples in 2009, making Uruguay the first South American country in which they could raise their own children.",
          "answer": "adoption"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of Uruguay, which names a 1933 Convention at which the Good Neighbor Policy was put forward.",
          "answer": [
            "Montevideo",
            "Montevideo Convention on the Rights and Duties of States"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian \"Hero of Two Worlds,\" who led the Redshirts in the Uruguayan Civil War.",
          "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi or Giuseppe Maria Garibaldi"
        },
        {
          "question": "War in which Uruguay fought with Brazil and Argentina against Paraguay from 1864 to 1870.",
          "answer": "War of the Triple Alliance"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"White\" faction that was defeated by the Colorados in the Guerra Grande.",
          "answer": [
            "Blancos or Partido Blanco",
            "or National Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name of a group of 33 \"Easterners\" who opposed Brazil in 1825, also found in the full, official name of Uruguay.",
          "answer": [
            "33 Orientals or Orientales",
            "Oriental Republic of Uruguay"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Father of Uruguayan Nationhood,\" who led the resistance against Spain and Portugal.",
          "answer": "José Gervasio Artigas or José Gervasio Artigas Arnal 9"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While serving as second-in-command to Robert Anderson, this person is thought to have been responsible for firing the first defensive shot during the Battle of Fort Sumter. A pasture belonging to Elihu Phinney was alleged to have been where this person made a (20 pts)",
        "certain innovation. A 71-year old mining engineer claimed that this person improved on an activity played by Otsego Academy students in Cooperstown, (10 pts)",
        "which was known as Town Bat. For ten points, name this Civil War general who was alleged to have invented baseball."
      ],
      "answer": "Abner Doubleday"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event’s central entity was criticized by Daniel Defoe, and it was prompted by the granting of a certain Asiento by the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Utrecht. This event developed after a certain company was granted a monopoly on the slave trade to an eponymous region of the Americas and began when stocks rose over a thousand percent without any realized profits due to the ongoing War of the Quadruple Alliance. Launching the premiership of Robert (10 pts)",
        "Walpole, for ten points, what is this event in which insider trading on debt consolidation and rampant false advertising caused an economic collapse in early 18th century Great Britain?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "South Sea Bubble",
        "the South Sea Company"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Among the targets of this operation was a man nicknamed \"The Red Prince\" who was thought to have been the leader of Force 17. A waiter was targeted in the Lillehammer Affair due to a misidentification during this operation, which is sometimes known as (20 pts)",
        "Operation Bayonet. Ali Hassan Salameh was eventually killed by a car bomb in Beirut during this mission, which was authorized by Golda Meir (10 pts)",
        "and carried out by Mossad. For ten points, name this Israeli assassination operation that was carried out in the aftermath of the Munich Massacre."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Operation Wrath of God",
        "Mivtza Za'am Ha'el",
        "Operation Bayonet before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The capital of this kingdom contained a temple complex dedicated to various aspects of Shiva, which was known as Sambor Prei Kuk. This kingdom is generally believed to have been a loose confederacy, and the rule of this kingdom is sometimes referred to as the Pre-Angkor (20 pts)",
        "period. This kingdom was first recorded by Zhou Daguan in The Customs of Cambodia, which records this kingdom as the successor of the Funan. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this Southeast Asian kingdom that was ruled from Isanapura and whose collapse led to the rise of the Khmer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chenla or Zhenla",
        "Chân Lạp"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This poet began meeting with a Cincinnati psychiatrist after spending days in front of the television in sorrow after JFK's death. This poet allegedly thought that the job of \"celestial navigation tower operator\" was \"the most poetic in the Air Force.\" The narrator of a work by this poet claimed to be (20 pts)",
        "\"Six miles from earth, loosed from its dream of life\" in a work in which the narrator \"woke to black flak\" in a certain area of a plane. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this World War Two veteran and poet of \"The Death of the Ball Turret Gunner.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Randall Jarrell 10 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After leaving Motown Records, this group regained popularity when Gerry Polci and Don Ciccone took over lead vocals on the album Who Loves You. Actor Joe Pesci introduced songwriter Bob Gaudio to (20 pts)",
        "Tommy DeVito and this group's frontman, who released solo songs rejected by the group, including \"My Eyes Adored You.\" The Four Lovers was the predecessor of this group, whose hits included \"Walk Like a Man,\" \"Sherry,\" (10 pts)",
        "and \"December, 1963.\" For ten points, name this early rock group depicted in the musical Jersey Boys."
      ],
      "answer": "Frankie Valli and the Four Seasons"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Howard Taft commissioned this architect to construct a summer capital for the Philippines at Baguio and redesign the permanent capital at Manila. This architect’s firm devised a “floating foundation” on which to build the Montauk Building, (20 pts)",
        "the first building deemed a “skyscraper,” and this architect's firm built Chicago’s Masonic Temple Building. As director of works, this architect was responsible for designing the White City for an 1892 to 1893 event. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, identify this head architect of the World’s Columbian Exposition who worked with John Wellborn Root."
      ],
      "answer": "Daniel Burnham or Daniel Hudson Burnham"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Diodorus Siculus claimed that this ruler was born of a fish-goddess and a mortal. According to legend, this ruler outfoxed satraps in Asia by donning armor and personally leading troops. One tradition holds that this wife of Ninus (20 pts)",
        "ordered the building of lofty terraces which inspired later writers to imagine the Hanging Gardens. Some sources credit this queen with constructing irrigation works along the Euphrates and overseeing the creation of defensive walls in (10 pts)",
        "Babylon. For ten points, name this legendary queen of Assyria."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Semiramis or Šammīrām",
        "or Samīrāmīs"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader precipitated the split of the Independent Social Democrats due to a pro-war stance, and this leader's son of the same name joined the pro-Soviet Socialist Unity Party. With Hugo Haase and Philipp Scheidemann, this leader formed the Council of People's Deputies after the November Revolution. (20 pts)",
        "Despite being a Social Democrat, this leader's administration suppressed left-wing revolts using the right-wing Freikorps, and this leader was succeeded by Paul von Hindenburg. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this first president of Weimar Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Friedrich Ebert"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the Hell Creek Formation, Steve Nicklas and Rob Sula discovered a North Dakota fossil site that was named after this city by Robert DePalma. The Decree of Canopus was discovered in this city and contains inscriptions in Greek and demotic. The 21st Dynasty was founded by Smendes in this city, which was the subject of a dig by (20 pts)",
        "Flinders Petrie. In a 1981 film, the U.S. Army attempts to recruit an archaeologist to recover the Ark of the Covenant from this city before the Nazis. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this ancient Egyptian city which is featured in Raiders of the Lost Ark."
      ],
      "answer": "Tanis 11 2025 V-JV National History Bowl National Championships Round 15"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader was succeeded in one post by Café Filho, who became the first Protestant to hold that position. Discovery of petroleum in this leader's country gave rise to the slogan \"The oil is ours!\" Coming to power during a (20 pts)",
        "Constitutionalist Revolution, this leader was supported by integralists and by the military in states like Paraiba and Minas Gerais. This non-Portuguese leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Estado Novo regime was once a member of the Legislative Assembly of Rio Grande do Sul. For ten points, name this president of Brazil prior to and during World War Two."
      ],
      "answer": "Getúlio Vargas or Getúlio Dornelles Vargas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one story, this kingdom’s capital city was home to a set of four fountains created by Hephaestus that sprayed milk, wine, oil, and water. This kingdom was home to a pair of bronze- mouthed bulls that breathed fire. While fleeing from this kingdom, a princess distracted her pursuers by cutting her brother Absyrtus (20 pts)",
        "into pieces and throwing them into the water. This kingdom was ruled by Aeëtes [[ay-EE-teez]], and this kingdom was the destination of the Argonauts on their quest for the golden fleece. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, identify this ancient Georgian kingdom along the Black Sea, the home of Medea."
      ],
      "answer": "Colchis or Egrisi"
    }
  ]
}